[SPEAKER_01]: So, why is sensuality dangerous?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is wanting pleasure dangerous?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's what we said.
[SPEAKER_01]: Understanding gratification, delight in the prospect of pleasure, the danger becomes apparent.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how else would you describe that danger?
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, why is it dangerous?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, so... On the basis of your presently enduring situation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, let's...
[SPEAKER_00]: I want to start with gratification.
[SPEAKER_00]: So...
[SPEAKER_00]: Right now, feeling a little bit unpleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the possibility of getting rid of that unpleasant feeling,
[SPEAKER_00]: By, I don't know, like figuring it out or... By doing something.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doing something or whatever, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there's a pleasure that comes from that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that pleasure is the pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what you were saying.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the pleasure... Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: ...is basically the possibility of that pain being taken away.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the pain that you're feeling, focusing or giving priority to the possibility of it disappearing, is felt pleasantly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Would you feel any, any, any, any degree of pleasure
[SPEAKER_01]: On account of possibility of pain going away, if you don't feel pain in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: The pain is primary.
[SPEAKER_01]: The pain is first.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, the extent of pleasure, the greatest sensual satisfaction, the mind fully gripped relishes...
[SPEAKER_01]: The most amazing thing you can experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's fully determined.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's basically so pleasant, because it's painful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the greater the prospect of escape, and the greater the prospect would be to a great pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is then the greater pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: But again, pleasure is not at the end of that pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's there.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is.
[SPEAKER_01]: While you're feeling that pleasure is because it's painful and you're feeling like you're escaping it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's all.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like...
[SPEAKER_01]: But if there is no pain, like when the pain disappears, when the itch disappears, your pleasure goes flat.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, is it like those, you know, those pictures where you see either two faces or a candlestick?
[SPEAKER_00]: You're basically... Oh, yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like...
[SPEAKER_01]: Magic eye.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, whatever, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, like, it's... it's the... it is... it's both a candlestick and its two faces.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like... it's just different way of looking at it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see... so, and you... basically, the two different ways of looking at it are in the right order and in the wrong order.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the wrong order, you're prioritizing the pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the right order, you're realizing, actually, that pleasure is fully dependent on this pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not just that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That pleasure is this pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, there is still a degree of separation when you say pleasure is within the pain, it's this, it's this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, you know, you have to express it somehow.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you want to be really, really accurate, that pleasure is the pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's also painful.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if there is no greater pain, that pleasure would be then seen as painful.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's all... it's all relative, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Did you hear that, Ben?
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: If there is no... if there is no greater pain...
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no greater pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, this currently presented prospect of evading the pain, which is pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That prospect of evading the pain would be also seen as unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the reason why pleasure... why pain is felt as pleasure when it comes to sensuality, is because it's underlined by even more pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: If there is no more pain, then the nature of sensuality would be apparent.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's painful.
[SPEAKER_01]: It always was painful.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what Buddha said in the... like the embers, the burning embers, the fire was always painful.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only reason it's pleasant is because it's less painful than your burning itch.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's relative.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's not even relative.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's painful in itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's relative in your perception of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I mean, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you...
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, nobody denies that there is... that you can feel pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what you're feeling pleasant is the pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but what I want to say, like, so... so, you've got this feeling and you go, oh, this is pleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not seeing that actually... That is... That pleasure there is actually painful.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's pain, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, see, as you just said, not seeing that, that's exactly the reason why it felt pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, no perspective on the arisen pain, you experience pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: And again, it's like... isn't... it seems to be more... it seems to be this, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: There's a tendency to focus and not see the wider picture.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're focusing in on the more particular pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not seeing that that's fully enclosed within this pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's why I would like... That's why it's painful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Any opportunity I have, I keep talking about... Go for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to learn to see things that are simultaneously present that you cannot focus on while you're focusing on something else.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're focusing on this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is part of the experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: The other part is that which is there simultaneously present in the background that you determine by your focusing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is why this contemplation or contemplation like this need to always be rooted in the situation as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: Otherwise, it becomes abstract.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you could see, if all you do is focusing, if all you do is observation of your nostrils, if all you do is, you know, going to methods and whatnot, if all you do is look at the objects of your experience, how can you then discern the context of it that you cannot focus on?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because your focus comes from that context.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you cannot discern that, how can you then see the underlying context of your current pleasure is pain?
[SPEAKER_00]: That's right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the context of the pleasure is pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means... Yeah, they're not on the same level.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: If the pain of the pleasure would be equally presented with the pleasure on the same level... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It would be obvious, easy choice for everyone.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the reason why everybody goes for pleasure is because you don't feel it painful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, okay, okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have no context on it, in it, in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's also because of craving for pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is because of pain that you have not seen.
[SPEAKER_01]: As we said, sensuality pressures you first.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's already pain, through and through.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you cannot escape that situation by any form of giving in to sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the only reason you'll be craving for pleasure is because you don't know the escape of the arisen pain of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, and that arisen... sorry, not knowing that escape of the arisen pressure, it's already... your context of your experience, it's already peripheral, it's already something you cannot focus on directly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if as... Because, see, focusing works towards the objects of your senses, but this is the basis for the whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: Experience of sense and sense objects.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where you're already pressured.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: If all you do is focusing on the sense objects, nostrils, nostrils, visual, visual, moving, tactile.
[SPEAKER_01]: If that's where your mind is, at the end of the sense objects, how can you then understand the peripheral context of the whole thing, when you never look in that way?
[SPEAKER_01]: But how can you... how can you focus?
[SPEAKER_01]: How can you look directly?
[SPEAKER_01]: Without the being.
[SPEAKER_01]: At the pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: that you're experiencing on account of a pleasant sight.
[SPEAKER_01]: Where is that pressure to see it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Where is the pressure?
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't see it like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: The pressure is... basically, you have been pressured.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how can you then know the pressure?
[SPEAKER_00]: Peripherally.
[SPEAKER_00]: Through the... through... through those... anything particular.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the necessary basis for... What is the necessary basis?
[SPEAKER_01]: Another necessary basis for pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: For pressure?
[SPEAKER_01]: Body?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, but how can you know pressure is there?
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, you know, your pressure to act.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because of how you're feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you directly observe with your senses your feelings?
[SPEAKER_01]: The feelings, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: There you go.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the whole domain of true feelings, what it's meant by feelings, pleasure, displeasure neutral, is completely invisible to those who refuse to give up the focusing methods.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's completely invisible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because all you do is look at things and you can't look at your feelings.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can feel your feelings.
[SPEAKER_00]: Basically, it's like the the the mood,
[SPEAKER_00]: The hue, the kind of tone that everything is kind of already affected by, it's not something that you can... it's like the weather.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't look at the weather, it's just like... Yeah, yeah, but even more so than the weather, it's just entirely a different domain where observation cannot apply.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the Buddha said, my teaching is for the one who knows how to feel.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to learn how to feel.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because most people, yeah, would just bundle up what they feel with what they observe and project it all out there and that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Negate it in doing so.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, people seek gratification, people experience happiness at the prospect of pleasure, of the senses, which is, you know, not necessarily just a coarse sexual pleasure or music or food.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sensual pleasure, sensuality, is on the domain of anything that causes you joy or sadness, if you lose it, on account of sense perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: So,
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Somebody chopping up the favorite tree in front of your kuti and it now exposes the view to the road.
[SPEAKER_01]: You get upset on account of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're upset on account of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unwanted visitors turn up, want to talk to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You get upset.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's on account of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wanted visitors don't turn up.
[SPEAKER_01]: You get upset.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's on account of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's an account of the experience of the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's how deep it goes.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not just saying no to particular pleasures.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, you need to first say no to particular pleasures of unwholesome nature, but in order to uproot it, if you uproot it, you'll be uprooting your whole domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, people turn to this happiness and gratification because, eh... the pressure is too unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind is untrained in regard to the pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: And has no other conceivable means of escape from that painful pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, give in.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I want to...
[SPEAKER_00]: I want to ask them, so then, what's the escape?
[SPEAKER_00]: But then... We'll get to the escape.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly, we're not... we're not there yet.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, well, I want to ask you, why then, if you were to free yourself, or see the extent
[SPEAKER_01]: of the gratification, see that no amount of pleasure you you might derive, you have derived, you are deriving, it's actually painful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That pleasure, while it's pleasant, it's actually painful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why then, if somebody is to free themselves from that, they would also free themselves from aversion and ill-will?
[SPEAKER_01]: As it's said to say.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's all about trying to... it's all about mastering the assumption of being able to master the feelings.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there's a... somebody does something, you become angry, and so you develop thoughts of... you have thoughts of ill will towards that person to help you deal with the anger.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a kind of a response to an arisen unpleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you derive some pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in that way, is it the same as a sensual response in regard to the enticing prospect of engaging with sense objects for the sake of pleasure?
[SPEAKER_00]: Seems to be like the same principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's completely the same principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And not just that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's probably about 80, maybe even 85 percent entirely the same motion.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only thing that varies is the... Is the object.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether the object is for you or, as in, in favor of you or against you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But usually that's how it starts.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the first point.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, this is completely against me or completely for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's actually the last bit of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The whole the whole structure of you resisting the presently enduring feeling that pressures you, is there the whole structure of you claiming for the prospect that basically, in its possibility, offers you, oh, maybe I can escape this, or maybe I can reduce this, or maybe I can replace this.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's entirely the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sensuality and ill-will are entirely the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why often anger mixes up with sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Especially with people's sexuality and
[SPEAKER_01]: As the Buddha said, Patujana knows only distraction of sensual gratification as the only means of the arising pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: To manage this pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the pain either comes from... the pain is either basically... so one feels pain and feels a pull towards sensual objects, you know, like... or one experiences pain in response to, I don't know, somebody does something that's displeasing to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's basically a move to overcome that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You again pull towards the sense object, which is dead person.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or rather pressured.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you're, you're focused.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you're focused, yes, rather than recognizing that, actually, I've already been pressured by this.
[SPEAKER_00]: I've already been subjected to this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, there's this feeling, enduring, and
[SPEAKER_00]: That came unbidden.
[SPEAKER_00]: The possibility of me having any mastery over that is... Well, it's already quite obviously false.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, here you are acting out of the possibility of mastering the circumstances that upset me in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if I could truly master them, if I am the master, I wouldn't have been upset in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or I wouldn't have been provoked sensually in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I wouldn't have been provoked aggressively, in terms of ill will, in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, why then?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why would then people still give in?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because they kind of know on a level... Yeah, but you don't... haven't seen that anything... that you can possibly experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: It has simply endured on its own.
[SPEAKER_00]: It has the nature to arise.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why haven't you seen that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's a beginningless.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because... because it is ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but why is ignorance still there?
[SPEAKER_01]: Ignorance is beginningless, but ignorance remaining there... Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: ...is, you know, it's not that you can't do anything about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, why is there nothing done about it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, don't leave the basis of feeling that we're talking about.
[SPEAKER_01]: The answer is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because of being still being pulled, it's... Sure, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, why are you pulled?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why are you pressured by the feeling?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or rather, how do you measure that you are pressured or pulled by the feeling?
[SPEAKER_00]: By the unpleasantness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is that what you mean?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, sort of, but even more accurately, how do you know that feeling pressured you?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, how can feeling pressure you?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're bothered by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, because you act out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't act out of it, it's not pressuring.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pressure is there, but you are not being pressured.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, your weakness is a measure by the act of weakness for which you're responsible.
[SPEAKER_01]: And why then would people give in?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is the enduring feeling
[SPEAKER_00]: Because they can't resist that feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: They can't withstand that feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: They can't endure it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, literally, if we boil down everything we've been saying in the last few talks regarding this topic, it all comes down to not knowing how to allow there is a feeling to endure on its own.
[SPEAKER_00]: On its own.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that is its nature.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, whenever you do anything to withstand that
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you ask yourself, why am I not allowing this?
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no answer.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a completely gratuitous assumption.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not allowing it because I never thought about it, really.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I'm not allowing it because I keep ignoring the issue of allowing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hence, ignorance is the most fundamental attitude that keeps us bound.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can't just... can you just... well, can you just choose?
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, right.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, from now on, I'm going to allow any feeling to endure.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, because, see, you've done that now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: On account of you want to get rid of the feelings.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't escape it so easily.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can't make a method out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, you can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, all you could do... Because it's always going to be secondary.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, all you can do is...
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I wanted to start with.
[SPEAKER_01]: All I teach is suffering and freedom from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: All I teach is what people feel and freedom from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: My teaching is for the one who knows.
[SPEAKER_01]: Knows what?
[SPEAKER_01]: He knows how to feel.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not in a wishy-washy way.
[SPEAKER_01]: You snowflake sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't feel like this.
[SPEAKER_01]: He knows how to feel as if...
[SPEAKER_01]: He knows how to not... How to let the feelings be the feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: How not to interfere with your recent feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he knows how to endure the endurance of feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, be mindful of the feeling that's enduring.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, I want to say, developing this context of
[SPEAKER_00]: I've been subjected to this.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that whenever you're seeing...
[SPEAKER_01]: But you don't need to be specifically developing that context.
[SPEAKER_01]: If that context presents itself, that's fine, on the basis of you allowing feeling to endure for as long as it wants to endure, and allowing it to change on a more particular level while remaining the same in its fundamental nature.
[SPEAKER_01]: That might reveal you that context, but not necessarily.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't need to go look for it, because you already have the necessary context, which is converging point of feeling that you're allowing to endure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you allow the feelings to endure by understanding... That you have no say in them.
[SPEAKER_01]: That you have no say in them, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That you can't do anything to affect it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why, you know, as we've described so many times, suffering is in you craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: In regard... regarding how you feel, not in how you're feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that is... that's pretty much the necessary basis for any context or contemplation you want to develop, if you want to do it rightly.
[SPEAKER_01]: The point of the presently enduring feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: But... okay, so... but we have the experience of, you know, what falls into the
[SPEAKER_00]: The idea that we do have some mastery over our feelings, because... Oh, really?
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how we don't fall into it, but basically... Basically, every patujanā thinks that they have some mastery over... assumes that they have some mastery over their feelings.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't, they don't really.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think...
[SPEAKER_01]: I remember even, even, even like way, way before...
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah, okay, okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: But...
[SPEAKER_01]: But the thing is that people do things in order to change their feelings.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what they... because they think they can do that, they wouldn't do it otherwise.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah, sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, like you go, ah, I'll... like you said, I'm depressed, I'll eat a nice cake, because that'll make me feel good, because I can somehow manage my feelings.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right, right, right, right, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, no, you have the cake and it does taste nice, you have a pleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I was aiming at.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I...
[SPEAKER_00]: I...
[SPEAKER_00]: I... it worked.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can control my feelings
[SPEAKER_01]: No, even that, the whole act of trying to do that, it's because of sadness, it's because of pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that is your motivation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, throughout doing this act, you're carrying on the motivation that you're trying to escape from.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you know that it doesn't work.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what you don't know is that you don't even have a say, in terms of control, when it comes to your environment.
[SPEAKER_01]: The appropriation of the senses and sense objects, that's where it takes place.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, you know you're just subjected to feelings,
[SPEAKER_01]: But you don't know that you have no right in claiming that these eyes, ears, nose, mouth, taste, touch, that are yours either.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, that's what everybody claims it is mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why I think I can indirectly protect my feelings, control my feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: I know, I have absolutely no say in them arising or ceasing if they want to go.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I, I'm fully committed to fighting for the environment.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That will prevent me from feeling such and such.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: They know you can't control the feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no direct relationship with your feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's an indirect managing the... And that's the key of ignorance and undoing the ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, what you already know, which is that there is no direct relationship with my feeling, I'm subject to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Stop ignoring it and stop trying to escape by the means of perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: From that necessary basis, even for such attempts of such escape.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, why are... why is sensuality dangerous?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is sensuality dangerous?
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what we... wasn't that where we were?
[SPEAKER_00]: Wasn't that your question earlier?
[SPEAKER_00]: Maybe.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is the gratification dangerous?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, that's what you asked.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is the gratification dangerous?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the whole thing is in sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Gratification, danger and escape, it's off the central domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: But why is the act of regarding pain as pleasant, dangerous?
[SPEAKER_00]: The act of regarding pain as pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or the act of feeling pain as pleasure, as in acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, it's not your act to feel it like this, it's your mistake.
[SPEAKER_01]: But why is acting out of that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Dangerous.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have a sensually enchanting object, prospect of it nearby.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can access it if you want.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that experience as a whole, that feeling, underlying feeling of that prospect that you are now in, is unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the pleasure that's wanted is not here.
[SPEAKER_01]: And why you want that pleasure is not because the thing is pleasant, but because the arising of the prospect is painful.
[SPEAKER_00]: That determines how much you want pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, as we described in the other talks, if the pleasure were truly contained in the objects, you wouldn't be able to know it before you're in touch with the objects.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you certainly would not be able to not feel pleasure when you're in touch with the objects, which also happens.
[SPEAKER_00]: The pleasure arises with the prospect of having that thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, because the prospect of having the thing is painful.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, following that... Because I've not got it, and I want it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Following that prospect,
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is that dangerous?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're reinforcing this wrong direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is the wrong direction wrong?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you aren't seeing what's painful as painful.
[SPEAKER_00]: You aren't seeing... Why is that risky?
[SPEAKER_01]: Danger.
[SPEAKER_01]: Risk.
[SPEAKER_01]: It says, you know, knowing gratification, the danger became apparent, the risk became apparent, as it should be said.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, why is it risky?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because... Because, actually, you have no control over the arising of pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: What pleasure?
[SPEAKER_01]: This pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: This pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: This possibility of the diminishing of the pain may not... You can't make that happen, no matter what you do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, no, it is a gratification, though.
[SPEAKER_01]: It does gratify to some extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: The burning embers do help Leper with his skin disease.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there's no risk there, then.
[SPEAKER_01]: If that would be the sole criteria.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there is a degree of gratification.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that can't be the risk.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what is then?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is the risk in that gratification that you can get?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, yeah, from the point of view of pain that just pressured me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Less pain is a form of escape.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's more agreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's more desirable, because it's pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, giving in to that, contains an inherent danger, a risk.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the risk?
[SPEAKER_00]: I want to say, because it's kind of...
[SPEAKER_00]: Keep reinforcing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's going to reinforce this particular direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: That happens as a result of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's not the apparent risk.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, oh, this result will happen after I do this.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is a risk in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Imply risk before you do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what risk is.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what means something's risky.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, this is risky.
[SPEAKER_01]: Knowing risk, you don't need to wait for the outcome to see the risk.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you don't know the risk before you do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, directly, before you do it, at the prospect of doing it, you discern that there is a risk in doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what's the risky bit?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the Buddha says it's... that these things are impermanent, unownable, subject to change.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which things?
[SPEAKER_01]: Feelings?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's say on the level of feelings.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's, again, if you don't feel unpleasant when the prospect of desirable object comes your way, you wouldn't be pressured to act towards it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, let's not leave that necessary basis out.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, go on.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's impermanent, unownable.
[SPEAKER_00]: So...
[SPEAKER_00]: This, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: The possibility of pleasure, the diminishing of...
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, which is seen as painful, is completely out of my hands and could change at any minute.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which one?
[SPEAKER_01]: What can change?
[SPEAKER_00]: The pleasure, the pain,
[SPEAKER_00]: But what if you change it the way you want to change?
[SPEAKER_00]: You get your desires gratified?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that could happen.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or it could go the other way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is that risky?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it could go the other way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's always a gamble.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And now... but, you know, 50-50 gambles, you have a good chance of winning.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but how?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, so, so, actually, so, so, because you're not in any control over the feelings that arise,
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm reaching out for some pleasure and it could end up in more pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's always a risk of any project end of the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, again, that's not a fundamental risk that would make you not go that way at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, as I said, from that point of view, it's 50-50.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But when the Buddha says that danger becomes apparent, means you cannot go back to sensuality ever again.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then he gives a simile, like a stone broken in half,
[SPEAKER_01]: They cannot be joined together.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like a vomited food, they cannot be desirable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like a dried-up leaf, they cannot become green again.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that'll be because you now see that whether...
[SPEAKER_00]: The danger is deeper.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever is... whatever feeling arises, whether it's painful or pleasant, that's something that you were subjected to.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that, in itself, is unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, that's on the level of you being pressured by the arisen prospect of sensuality, or something like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But even being... even being hit by pleasure is something that you were hit by.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's what I'm saying.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hit by the prospect of sensuality, which is regarded as pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's absolutely true.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, these things, they kind of change in a way of like, oh, look, now I have an opportunity for this great desire, for gratification of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's on... oh, that's on the... like that... that fundamental... that still endures.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're affected by that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And while you're affected by that desire, that's the only way you'll be acting to fulfill the desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: If the desire were not unpleasant in its nature, you wouldn't be pressured to do anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: And pressuring to do anything, or following the pressure to do anything, is where gratification is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the Buddha said, when you understand that, you understand the danger.
[SPEAKER_01]: The danger becomes apparent.
[SPEAKER_00]: The danger of your act, not of what you are subjected to.
[SPEAKER_00]: The danger of responding to the fact that you are pressured.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is it dangerous to do that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the fact that you are pressured by, say, let's stick to the example, a central object that offers itself, you can have it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you have it to get pleasure from it and escape from the displeasure of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's in itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not saying that, you're subjected to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's the act of gratification, it's the act of seeking that pleasure, in order to escape pain, that reveals the danger, that's the danger in doing it, makes it dangerous.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means in itself, these things arising on their own, it's just how they are.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's your way of involving yourself with them, that reveals the danger.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's your way of...
[SPEAKER_01]: The danger becomes apparent...
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Following the gratification.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is that dangerous?
[SPEAKER_00]: How dare you?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, being pressured by the central object that's in front of you, that you can have now, that's the reason state of affairs.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the arisen experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: The unpleasant feeling of not having this, the mind grip wanting it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The thing as a whole has arisen as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You, having desire towards it, acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're then responding to something which has arisen, which I have no... Yeah, but see, that's again how you're explaining it linearly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: The point is, can you act towards it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Without implying that you want that same thing that you're acting towards to change.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, your experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: Would you be acting out of being pressured by the desire?
[SPEAKER_01]: Could you be acting out of being pressured by the desire without implying, I want to change this?
[SPEAKER_01]: I want this changed.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't want this situation to be like that, I want it to be like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even if there is a... like, if you don't practice restraint, if you're unrestrained householder layman, who lives, like, just follows his sensual pleasures, say, a new object of sensuality appears,
[SPEAKER_01]: And he knows he'll have it.
[SPEAKER_01]: He is going for it in a second.
[SPEAKER_01]: The experience of his desire, that has been manifested when he became aware of the object, is unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's not pleasant enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: From his point of view.
[SPEAKER_00]: This situation I'm in now, is not pleasant enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: It could be more pleasant if I go... if I get that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just... it's just...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, whichever way you take it, fundamentally, you're avoiding pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you want... Because you want something to change.
[SPEAKER_01]: Less pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you don't... if you know you can't change it, doesn't mean you... you still want change.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the risk.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wanting change.
[SPEAKER_01]: And can you engage, can you give in, can you act out of your desire without implying you want change?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what desire is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either change of this pleasure for more pleasure, or change of this pain for less pain, or change of this pleasure with... this pain for complete pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what change.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, it's the change that made you pressure... that pressured you in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: The change pressured me in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because what else is arising of desire than change of circumstances that you were pressured by?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you mean something changed?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I mean, like, there was no sensual object here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And now there is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: It changed.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, something changed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: On account of which, I now find that there's this possibility of pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can that possibility of pleasure be acted out without approving and implicitly wanting more change?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, the change is the only reason you were pressured in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, your only means of escaping change is to approve the change, which makes you more liable to pressure of change.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, for a leper with a skin disease, fire, cauterizing his wound, is the only means of escape that he knows, that it's making his wounds even worse, that he needs to cauterize even more, that will make the wounds even worse, that he needs to cauterize more.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the danger of gratification, of following the desire, is the implicit approval, implicit appropriation, implicit wanting of change.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, it's because of the change that you have this desire that bothers you in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you make yourself liable to the risk by doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, the things have changed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things change on their own.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, as I said,
[SPEAKER_01]: How do you know you're pressured by feelings?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you give in.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't give in, if you stop giving in to the pressure of feelings, you can't say anymore, feelings pressure me.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the measure of how much you're pressured is the measure of how much you acted out of feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even mentally.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even mentally, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, can you say that the the danger is the change?
[SPEAKER_00]: The danger is change.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you just see change in things, that's not the danger that you need.
[SPEAKER_01]: You won't see it as dangerous.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to see that you're giving in, your approval, you're welcoming, delighting in, being happy on account of the prospect of satisfying desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: Cannot be done without implying change.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, cannot be done without making yourself subjected to the risk of change.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is the greatest risk?
[SPEAKER_01]: Life changes for death.
[SPEAKER_00]: Gain changes for loss.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, why is change dangerous?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can ask that question now.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's the gratification reveals the danger, because there is no gratification without implicit change.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, change is dangerous.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is change dangerous?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because...
[SPEAKER_00]: I think the idea...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, because change is not this continuous... things continuously just change.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like... No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not... Go on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Basically, it's something... Change is completely, like... comes from a completely conceivable direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: I find that things have already changed.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can't... it's something that's totally beyond my power, me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Abrupt.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It happens to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just as we describe in terms of feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, even people who know, people who are not relinquishing sensuality, practicing dhamma, they still know you can't control feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're subjected to them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So...
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so you can't look at something change, rather you just go, well, that's changed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, the change we talk about is not the change of my observation, which is fully on, like, what I want to do, or some, like, metaphysical theory.
[SPEAKER_01]: The change is the change of how you feel.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you're not saying that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, as I said, you can only understand gratification if you understand the pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can only understand the danger if you understood gratification.
[SPEAKER_01]: That means understanding all the pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: What's the pressure other than feeling?
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence, if you still think, if a person still think on the level of, oh, this is one thing, one thing changes, second thing, second thing, that has nothing to do with what we are talking about.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's just the domain of science and physics, which doesn't have the observer that is self-aware.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you account for feelings in physics and mathematics?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, there you go.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot account for the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Full stop.
[SPEAKER_00]: You... yeah, so basically...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, change is change on the emotional level.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's exactly what Buddha said when he asked people, oh, so what?
[SPEAKER_01]: Your pleasure... your... your... your self is... is... is your pleasure?
[SPEAKER_01]: He says, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, so why don't you... why... why... why are you then feeling pain sometimes?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why are you sometimes feeling neutral?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if your feeling is yours, as in, if you would be in control,
[SPEAKER_01]: It wouldn't change.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It would always be the way you want it to be.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you are subject to change.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Fundamentally, at the level of feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: The direction... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: The direction where change comes from, as you said, it's completely inconceivable to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why it's risky.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if something... if you have absolutely no idea how can this change, and whether it's going to change in agreeable way or non-agreeable way,
[SPEAKER_01]: And what extent of the non-agreeable way?
[SPEAKER_01]: And what harm of the non-agreeable way?
[SPEAKER_01]: If all those things you cannot even account for in theory, would you regard that thing as non-risk-free?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: It would be extremely risky.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the danger.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is the danger.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, seeing change over there, you don't see the danger.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to see the right order of things for danger to become apparent, as the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the right order is, first, you need to understand the gratification of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And to understand the gratification of it, you have to, first of all, see...
[SPEAKER_01]: Learn how to feel.
[SPEAKER_01]: ...the fact that you've been pressured.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Allow the feeling, the pressures you took with you, stop trying to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Through explaining it, through following a meditation technique, through trying to sort of deny it, to try to say, oh, well, look, this body is made of atoms and sensations, nothing is real.
[SPEAKER_01]: All form of management of that which pressures you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the only reason you're doing it is because you're still pressured.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you've been pressured, there's a feeling, there's gratification.
[SPEAKER_01]: Gratification already starts at the prospect of changing the feeling that you don't want.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Changing pleasure for more pleasure, changing pain for less pain, changing your thought for, basically, distraction, not being aware of it, because it's unpleasant when you're aware of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's inconceivable to give in to desire without wanting, implying that change.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, it's that change.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no saying that puts you in this position in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence, you keep yourself... bound within that same cycle of... ...willingly bound in that absolutely, like, not even a cycle, like a... just a perpetual domain of perpetual risk.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Chaos.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what's then, like, the easiest way to deal with it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Ignore it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's, basically, I'm just... Yeah, that being prey to suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's the definition of it, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Being subject to suffering, being prey to suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what being subject to suffering... That's what being subject to suffering means.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means, I don't necessarily need to be suffering now.
[SPEAKER_01]: I am subject to suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the nature, in my own nature, I can be affected by suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the only way to stop that is to see the danger involved in wanting things to change, to be otherwise than they are.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you want things to change without craving?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what craving is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence, craving is the root of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: No craving, no suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even amidst the adverse circumstances that would otherwise make you suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's when the danger becomes apparent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not the danger of this, the danger of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: The danger of me, if I want this, that's how I already make myself liable to that danger.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, restraining yourself in regard to sensuality prevents some danger, but if you still want it in your mind, to that extent you're still liable to suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: When things change the way you don't want them to.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, when your feelings change the way you don't want them to.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then you realize that even your sense of control towards perceptions, intentions and so on, it's completely secondary to the fundamental liability to the feeling that you have no say in.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, then, your control is not really in your...
[SPEAKER_01]: This is subject to change.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your control, then, is not really your control.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the inherent nature of feelings.
[SPEAKER_00]: They are subject to change.
[SPEAKER_00]: They are of the nature to change.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nature to be otherwise.
[SPEAKER_01]: The parināma dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: But again, that's not what the danger is.
[SPEAKER_00]: The danger isn't the fact that...
[SPEAKER_00]: The danger is...
[SPEAKER_00]: The danger is the...
[SPEAKER_00]: He's wanting them to change.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's approving.
[SPEAKER_01]: The danger is approving of change, through implicitly approving of change, through giving it to a desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, you know change is a problem because it bothers you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, the only means of getting rid of it is approving the means of change.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence the utter discrepancy and contradiction on a very existential level.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence the suffering, the liability to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not dangerous that things change.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's dangerous you to use means of change to change things.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where the danger is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you insert yourself and that's why you become subject to these things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Trying to change.
[SPEAKER_00]: Change.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I don't want change.
[SPEAKER_01]: And thus, I'll change it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll change it.
Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the inherent condensed principle of sensuality, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: And your will.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't want this change, so I change it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because I don't know anything other than change.
[SPEAKER_01]: So the... this change is not the risk.
[SPEAKER_01]: Outcome of me changing it is not the risk.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or it's all secondary to the risk.
[SPEAKER_01]: The risk is the fact that I still approve of that option, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where the danger is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so you're keeping it alive.
[SPEAKER_01]: Keep yourself bound to it fully.
[SPEAKER_01]: Keep yourself fully subjected to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, your wounds won't heal, because you keep burning them, scratching them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which leads to the question then, so what is the escape?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why do you think it's escape based on this?
[SPEAKER_01]: Allowing whatever feeling it is to endure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, gratification is understood, reveals the danger, thus the escape is then understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is to not
[SPEAKER_00]: Make to not want to change the arisen feeling, the enduring feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but you can't quite choose to not want that.
[SPEAKER_01]: How can you then not want it?
[SPEAKER_01]: How can you then escape it?
[SPEAKER_01]: If you can't just make a choice, like, I don't want this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, by understanding that... Yeah, what does that entail?
[SPEAKER_00]: Understanding the nature of feeling is that
[SPEAKER_00]: It's... it's not something I can change.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but needs to be more accurate.
[SPEAKER_00]: More pinpoint.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, as we established then...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, we said...
[SPEAKER_01]: Wanting change.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is implicit risk.
[SPEAKER_01]: Approving of change through your wanting.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is change.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is changed and I want... My situation has changed and I want that to change.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the danger.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the contradiction.
[SPEAKER_01]: What are you escaping from?
[SPEAKER_00]: The currently enduring feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what does the word escape mean?
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, I know what the escape means, but what is it escape from?
[SPEAKER_00]: Suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: What suffering?
[SPEAKER_00]: The suffering on account of the enduring feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: The craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, is the craving the enduring feeling?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's your response to the enduring feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's where suffering is?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not on the level of enduring feeling?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, why you need to allow the enduring feeling to be, in order to escape it?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the allowing, the not fighting, the not...
[SPEAKER_00]: But what if you allow it for the purpose of... Then, you're... okay, then, you're still bound up with... that's correct.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you're not basically doing it on the right level, yeah?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you're crazy, yeah?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what needs to be drilled and drilled and drilled.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, escape, it's escape of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Escape from the risk.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Escape from that danger.
[SPEAKER_00]: Escape from the danger, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how do you escape wanting to change?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, hold on, let me phrase it like this then.
[SPEAKER_01]: How do you then escape the danger that is solely, fully, always, completely implicit only when you choose to act this way?
[SPEAKER_01]: As I said, there is no danger in change of random things.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's danger when you imply change for the sake of change that you're subjected to.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, your implication, your craving, your wanting to change it, that's where danger is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not in the things.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's in your... Not in the things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's in your response.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's in your attitude.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how do you... how do you... like... okay, let me put it like this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you want... can you have a desire... can you act towards
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you then don't regard it as pleasurable, how can you regard it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Not want it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or how can you regard it as unpleasurable?
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's put it like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: By seeing danger in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, by seeing the danger in it, you turn away from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You stop finding it pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: You see that thing as unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: You find it pleasurable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you want this pleasure?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you want this pleasure?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the escape.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no step you need to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, the danger is the escape.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just have to clarify the gratification which will reveal the danger which will make the escape possible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same with the four noble truths, by the way.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like one, two, three, four.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's one within the other, just different aspects of the
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the escape of not wanting that which you used to want.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's seeing sense... without... sense... sense desires, the things that you... that you want, that you're... that you're... that you saw as a... as a possibility for pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Have to be careful there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not objects of your senses, because now people will go around saying like, oh, that's danger.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it's not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's you staring at it in the first
[SPEAKER_00]: First, what you regard, what you regarded as a possibility for pleasure, you now see as the, as it says in the suttas, the charcoal pit.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see that thing is no longer seen as desirable, as enticing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's now seen as dangerous.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, even more accurately, it's the same charcoal pit you used to use to burn your, your wounds.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's your attitude towards it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That you were deriving pleasure from.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the same charcoal pit that's now extremely painful because your wounds have healed.
[SPEAKER_01]: And actually, in that same sutra, the Buddha says that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: What if that man that's now healed gets grabbed by the two stronger men and you want to take him back to the fire and drop him in?
[SPEAKER_01]: He'd be everywhere, kicking and screaming.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not like to go around, oh, so sense objects are painful.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's already... you already missed... missed the right basis of seeing that.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is painful is you already engaging with sense objects.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether you approve or disapprove of them, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why I was explaining, like, most people do their subha quite wrongly.
[SPEAKER_01]: They try to use a subha perception to replace the perception of attraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: You discern a subha within it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And sure, corpses, dead bodies, things like that, can show you that sign... sign is always peripheral to what you're looking at.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the definition of a sign, by the way, even in colloquial terms.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't walk on grass.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're staring at the board.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not staring at the command of people not walking on the grass.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's implicit in the letters on the board.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the object of your perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: The sign is in your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: When there is the pull toward sense object or aversion toward sense object, you need to discern what the sign, the context of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you realize that whether I approve or disapprove of it,
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't question the fact that I want to, like, get rid of the pressure that it exerts over me.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I don't question the fact that I imply desirable change, yet it's because of change that I suffer in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's where the danger is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence, the sensory strength and virtue in sīla must, it's absolutely not negotiable, must be thoroughly developed beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there's a slightest leak down the direction of physical action and verbal action and so on, you're not gonna see it on the right level of the right sign, of the right context.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the danger for somebody who starts from the point of view of ignorance, the danger is on the level of engagement.
[SPEAKER_01]: Positive or negative, it doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: I want this, I don't want this.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're already focused on this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why would you be focused on this, unless you're already pressured by it, either for wanting more or not wanting it at all?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or denying it, or fighting it, or...
[SPEAKER_00]: Hence, stop.
[SPEAKER_01]: Stop your focusing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Stop staring and trying to find the answer through, like, a revelation of your perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: And look back at the fact that you've already been pressured.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not directly.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you look back, you'll be staring at that.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, I mean, just, just, like... Whatever you looked at, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Discern the context of it while you're looking at it.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, when there is the experience of pressure, I'm pressured by somebody said something upsetting, or I'm pressured by somebody revealed a prospect to central pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either way, it exerts pressure on me.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the experience of prospect of central pleasure, I'm pressured by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That sensual object, that possibility, couldn't be there without this pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, now I need to... what I need to do is not go in automatically, habitually, physically, and just get in touch with that object.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, once I restrain, still, I still want it on the level of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: And now you can start doing the work we talk about on the level of your mind, which is where sensuality is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what you do on the level of the mind is... so,
[SPEAKER_01]: You are pressured.
[SPEAKER_01]: There cannot be any conceivable form of engagement without implicit desire to get rid of that painful pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: No amount of pleasure, nothing, no endgame, no result there or there, later on in time, can be anywhere else rooted except in me not wanting this pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, again, if you were not pressured in the first place, could you conceive any desire towards the outcome?
[SPEAKER_00]: Inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that, when you realize, when you start realizing that, then you see that there is absolutely no such thing as the end gratification that will replace the pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: The sole pleasure of gratification is because of the presently enduring pain, and it endures throughout that time.
[SPEAKER_00]: The pain of being pressured?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not on you, but now you're clearly acting, having desire, not restraining desire, not understanding desire, that's on you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why the risk is on you, because that's where the risk is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you then want anything, even if you're not acting out of?
[SPEAKER_01]: If you know that what you want is actually extremely, extremely dangerous and deadly, and there is absolutely no basis for pleasure and safety in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: The danger becomes apparent then.
[SPEAKER_01]: And now that you don't want it, that's how you escape it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that was the only connection, by the way.
[SPEAKER_01]: These things cannot answer you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are the one who answers them.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's again, Buddha said that many times, but in that particular sutta, it's because people take.
[SPEAKER_01]: That which doesn't belong to them, the māra does what he wants, controls them.
[SPEAKER_01]: They make themselves subject to his control.
[SPEAKER_01]: What are the things that belong to māra, not to people, and people take them?
[SPEAKER_01]: Sight, sound...
[SPEAKER_00]: The eye.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the eye, the eye objects, the ear, the...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, the sixth sense space, and everything else you can get from it, within it, corresponding to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The eye is mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the eye is not yours, the nose, the entire body, the entire experience as a whole cannot be yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you regard it as yours?
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't want it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you regard it as yours, if it's seen as painful?
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you regard it as yours, if it's seen as constantly oppressing you?
[SPEAKER_00]: Not at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, not seeing it, in such and such, in all these manners, that's why you regard it as yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: You start seeing it, you can't regard it as yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you don't need to then choose the escape.
[SPEAKER_01]: The escape is automatic.
[SPEAKER_01]: Understanding anicca correctly, understanding dukkha correctly,
[SPEAKER_01]: Anatta is automatic.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the necessary result of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not, oh, now I do the anatta.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now I do the anatta.